<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Friendly letter to all young men shewing the benefit of a religious and friendly reproof, conversation and admonition, and not only to live good lives themselves but to incourage others to do the same : with a letter to masters of families : to which is added a specimen of the rules and orders of the religious societies, as now practiced in the cities of London and Westminster.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2223A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26731</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09527559</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09527559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1331:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Friendly letter to all young men shewing the benefit of a religious and friendly reproof, conversation and admonition, and not only to live good lives themselves but to incourage others to do the same : with a letter to masters of families : to which is added a specimen of the rules and orders of the religious societies, as now practiced in the cities of London and Westminster.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The fifth edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[7], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by W. Downing,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Societies, etc.</term>
               <term>Young men --  Conduct of life.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43505:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43505:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Friendly Letter</hi> TO ALL YOUNG MEN, Shewing the Benefit of a Religious and Friendly <hi>Reproof, Converſation, &amp; Admonition;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not only to live good Lives them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but to incourage others to do the ſame. With a Letter to Maſters of Families.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A Specimen of the <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> of the <hi>Religious Societies,</hi> as now Practiſed in the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fifth Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember thy Creator in the Days of thy Youth,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Eccleſ. 12. 1.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>W. Downing</hi> in <hi>Bartholomew-Cloſe</hi> near <hi>Weſt-Smithfield,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43505:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> Bookſeller <hi>being upon Printing another Edition of the Friendly Letter to all Young Men, I thought it might not be amiſs, in order to the Increaſing theſe</hi> Religious Societies, <hi>to prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe Excellent</hi> Goſpel Rules <hi>and</hi> Orders <hi>the</hi> Firſt Edition <hi>ſpeaks of, being ſuch as have been approved of by many Eminent Divines of the</hi> Church of England, <hi>and which are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Practice of the best Chriſtians, in the first and purest Ages of the Church, and ſuch as I hope will induce the</hi> Reader <hi>to ſet up ſuch a</hi> Religious Society <hi>amongst his</hi> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, <hi>where much good may be done, as there</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43505:2"/> 
               <hi>hath already been by them in the Cities of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and ſeveral other Places in this Kingdom, as well as in</hi> Ireland; <hi>(by which means great Numbers of</hi> poor Houſe-keepers <hi>have been</hi> Relieved, poor Children <hi>kept to</hi> School, <hi>and after put</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices.) <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, <hi>in his</hi> Eſſay <hi>on the Memory of our late Gracious Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN,</hi> page 118. <hi>gives this Account of her Opinion and Satisfaction of theſe</hi> Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>in theſe Words;</hi> She did hearken care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully after every thing that ſeemed to give ſome hope that the next Generation ſhould be better than the preſent, with a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Attention: She heard of a Spirit of Devotion and Piety that was ſpreading it ſelf among the Youth of this great City, with a true Satisfaction: She enquired often and much about it, and was glad to hear it went on and prevailed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some of theſe</hi> Societies <hi>have (by their pious Examples) influenced</hi> Diſſenters <hi>to come to Church, and ſeveral</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>and</hi> Quakers <hi>to Baptiſm; and have been a means of preſerving from</hi> Popery <hi>ſeveral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſteady and Wavering people, in the late times: And being not unſenſible of their own and others Infirmities, they keep up theſe</hi> Societies, <hi>in meeting together once a Week, that they may</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43505:3"/> 
               <hi>re-inforce on each others Minds the great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of</hi> Chriſtianity, <hi>in order to the carrying on thoſe good Works they are already ingaged in, and which, I hope, will induce the Reader to an Imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Deſign in this little</hi> Treatiſe <hi>is only to aſſist the Ignorant, and thoſe who are willing to form themſelves into</hi> Societies, <hi>they being ſo very beneficial to Youth, as well as to thoſe of Riper Years. For as there is nothing in its ſelf more Excellent than</hi> Religion; <hi>ſo you cannot imagine the unſpeakable Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages a</hi> Pious Youth <hi>gains by the Practice of it in theſe Societies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do but conſider how welcome a</hi> Young Convert <hi>is to God: It was to young</hi> Samuel <hi>that</hi> God <hi>revealed himſelf, to ſhew how much He honoured a young Propher,</hi> 1 Sam. 3. 1. <hi>And you know that St.</hi> John, <hi>the Youngest of all the Diſciples, is the only Perſon of all the Twelve, who was permitted to lean on our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Boſom at the last Supper, as dearest in Affection to Him, and who is called,</hi> the Diſciple whom Jeſus loved, <hi>John 13. 23. And this is ſuitable to that Gracious Promiſe which God hath made, to incourage all Young Perſons to ſerve Him;</hi> I love them that love me, and they that ſeek me early ſhall find me, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 7.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43505:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O Young Man, whoſoever thou art, that readeſt this Promiſe, let it excite in thee a great Zeal to ſeek God, and to ſeek Him early; for if thou doſt ſeek, thou art ſure to find Him: thou art ſure when thou hast found Him, he will love thee, and thou ſhalt reap all the happy effects of God's Infinite Love, and of an early Piety; and the Pleaſure of well-doing that thou wilt at preſent feel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Think if you can how unconceivable a Joy it will be to you, when in your Elder years you can reflect on your well-ſpent time, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of your Youth; how great a Conſolation it will be to you when you come to your Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; how eaſie it will render your Accounts at the great Day of Judgment; and how much a whole Life ſpent in God's Service will increaſe your Glory in the other World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore conſider the vast Neceſſity and the Advantage there is of beginning to be good betimes; for we know not but that the next mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may determine our Everlaſting Fate; and the hopes of Heaven, which we have now in our Hands, may ſlip from us before to Morrow Morning, and ſo leave us deſperate for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore conſider what a dreadful venture you run, if you delay your Time of Salvation, or put it off from Day to Day; and the longer</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43505:4"/> 
               <hi>you delay, the more averſe you will be to it; for your Luſts will every Day grow dearer and dearer unto you, and you will find your ſelves more and more unwilling to part with them: Therefore make no delay, but take the Wiſe Man's Advice, and</hi> make no tarrying to turn to the Lord, and put it not off from Day to Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And let this Conſideration ingage you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to think what Engagements you ly under to an Holy Life by your own Profeſſion,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes <hi>and</hi> Vows; <hi>for you profeſs and call your ſelves Chriſtians, Followers of Christ, ought you not then to follow his Example, and obey his Commands, if you will make good that Name? You will think it a great Diſgrace not to be taken for</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>but for a</hi> Turk <hi>or</hi> Jew: <hi>Beware then, lest you bring this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace upon your ſelf by an unchriſtian Temper of Mind, and ill courſe of Life; for if you are Falſe, or Cruel; Covetous, or Luſtful; Proud, or Revengeful, like a</hi> Turk <hi>or</hi> Heathen, <hi>it matters little what you call your ſelf: For he is not a</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>that is one outwardly; but he that hath</hi> the ſame Mind and Spirit that was in Chriſt Jeſus: <hi>For God will not, at the Last Day, Judge Men by their Names and Titles, but by their Hearts and Lives; only it will go much worſe with a Man that</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43505:4"/> 
               <hi>calls himſelf a</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>and lives like a</hi> Turk <hi>or</hi> Infidel. <hi>Therefore make no Delay about a</hi> Holy Life, <hi>but ſtrive, and uſe your utmost endeavour to make your ſelf what you will wiſh to be when you come to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And one great means to effect this will be, to keep ſuch Company as are already ingaged in a Holy Life; for to hear the Diſcourſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Men delights us, and their Company is the most Beneficial; and it is</hi> That <hi>which I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend in the following</hi> Letter, <hi>and that I would deſire you to read ſeriouſly over and over again, not as School-Boys do their Leſſons; but apply it to your ſelf as you read, and conſider whether you are of ſuch a Temper or no that this</hi> Letter <hi>recommends; and if you are, perſevere in it to the end, remembring that gracious Promiſe,</hi> He that endureth to the End ſhall be ſaved; <hi>if you are not, make no delay, but ſtrive to find out ſome of thoſe Men that live good Lives, and they will be a Help and Benefit to you: But above all, acquaint your ſelf with a</hi> ſober Miniſter, <hi>and conſult him with the great concernments of your Soul: Remember alway that this is a Work that must not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed; for we know not what a Day may bring forth: Therefore take St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s Advice, with which I ſhall conclude,</hi> Rom. 13. 12, 13, 14. Let us therefore caſt off the Works of
<pb facs="tcp:43505:5"/> Darkneſs, and let us put on the Armor of Light. Let us walk Honeſtly as in the Day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and Envying. But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no Proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfill the Luſts thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 20, 21. Now the God of Peace that brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus, that Great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Make you perfect in every good Work to do his Will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his Sight, through Jeſus Chriſt; to whom be Glory for ever and ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43505:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Friendly Letter</hi> TO ALL YOUNG MEN, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DEarly Beloved Brethren, and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it is to you that I now Write, as a Friend and a Brother; for ſuch we ſhould all be one to another; and our Saviour makes it the great viſible Badge of Chriſtianity; <hi>By this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have Love one for another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this Divine Grace of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> being the Foundation of all <hi>Religion,</hi> let it ſhew its ſelf that it is in our Hearts, by a true and ſincere Deſire of <hi>doing Good</hi> to one another, and to all Men, to their precious and Immortal Souls; and let us look upon it as our Duty, the Endeavouring to ſave them; and the only means whereby to effect that Work is, to promote Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43505:6"/> in the World, and Holineſs of Life; for <hi>without Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, to the Promoting of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> in the World, nothing is more effectual than the frequent Converſation of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with each other: <hi>This</hi> is a Truth that may be manifeſted from divers Arguments: This is that therefore which in this <hi>Letter</hi> I would chiefly recommend to you; to wit, <hi>Chriſtian Converſation and Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man is a Creature made for Society; it is by <hi>That</hi> that he eaſes his Mind, by Communicating his Thoughts; it is by <hi>That</hi> that he receives Comfort, by the Counſel of others, and gets Wiſdom by their Admonition and Advice; nay, it is by <hi>That</hi> (as an Inſtrument by which the Holy Spirit does work) that he gets Grace: For all Converſation is of an aſſimilating Nature; that is, it makes Men become like to thoſe they converſe withall; and, conſequently, the ſame effect may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably hop'd for from <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. And this may be further manifeſted from the Practice of Satan, whoſe Buſineſs it is therefore, in the firſt place, to divert Men from Chriſtian Converſation; and this he effects, <hi>Firſt,</hi> By bringing Reproach on ſuch Aſſemblies, as <hi>Phanatical,</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43505:6"/> tending to <hi>Schiſm,</hi> thereby affrighting weak Chriſtians, who have not ſtrength to indure Shame for the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or that have not Judgment to determine rightly of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm</hi> and <hi>Schiſm.</hi> And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> by Furniſhing of Men with Diverſity of other Converſation; and for this End he has ſet up <hi>Prophane and Atheiſtical Clubs</hi> in <hi>Taverns</hi> and <hi>Ale-Houſes,</hi> and other <hi>Merry Meetings,</hi> which tend much to the Promoting of his Kingdom; becauſe (beſide other Evils) they keep Men from ſerious and pious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; for, ſee what is the Diſcourſe of every <hi>Tavern-Club,</hi> of every <hi>Coffee-Houſe-Table,</hi> of every <hi>Merry Meeting.</hi> What Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe do you there meet with that is <hi>ſeaſon'd with Grace,</hi> and <hi>to the uſe of Edifying,</hi> which, the Apoſtle tells us, all our Diſcourſe ought to be? It were to be wiſh'd, that it were no worſe than <hi>Idle;</hi> and yet, <hi>for every Idle Word that Men ſhall ſpeak,</hi> (our Saviour aſſures us) <hi>they ſhall give an Account at the Day of Judgment.</hi> And if there ſhould be ſome good Chriſtians among them in ſuch Places, yet, How are they daunted? How little Courage have they to promote any ſpiritual or ſavory Diſcourſe? How aſhamed to reprove any Prophaneneſs or filthy Talk? till, by degrees, from uſing to hear ſuch,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43505:7"/> things without Reproving them, they grow cold in their Zeal for Religion, and, at length, become inſenſible: ſo very true it is what the Apoſtle ſays, that <hi>Evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication corrupts</hi> even <hi>good Manners:</hi> It is like an infectious Diſeaſe, it gets into our Nature, and we know not how, and ſpreads its ſelf into all our Words and Actions.</p>
            <p>This is a true Reaſon why Chriſtians are ſo cold in their Devotions, ſo tardy in their Journey Heaven-ward, even becauſe they converſe too much with the Men of the World, which, the Holy Ghoſt aſſures us, is <hi>Enmity to God:</hi> becauſe they are ſo far taken with one Man's Wit, another's good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, a third's Raillery, as to wink at his Prophaneneſs, his lewd Jeſts, his impudent Slander; and ſo by growing cool in their Zeal for Virtue, Piety, and the Glory of <hi>God,</hi> they at length ſink inſenſibly into an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking State; whereas if we followed the Apoſtle's Advice, <hi>with a Brother that were a Fornicator, or a Worldling, no not to eat,</hi> we ſhould then be ſure of keeping alive that Fervor and Holy Zeal in our Hearts, which alone denominate us Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now ſince it is moſt manifeſt, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing does more promote the Kingdom of <hi>Satan</hi> than theſe <hi>publick Clubs,</hi> Why ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43505:7"/> not good Chriſtians countermine them, by making <hi>Sober Societies</hi> among themſelves? For in Company with Religious Perſons, one is tempted to utter thoſe good things which weak Chriſtians are aſhamed to ſpeak before the Wicked; and we ſhould have great Incouragement to ſpeak what might be <hi>to the uſe of Edifying, and miniſtring Grace to the Hearers,</hi> and ſhould our ſelves ſoon find the Benefit of keeping ſuch Company. <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith Holy <hi>David) the Companion of all thoſe that fear Thee, and keep thy Righteous Judgments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Can a Man touch Pitch,</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>and not be defiled therewith? Can a Man carry Fire in his Boſom, and his Cloaths not be burnt?</hi> So neither can a Man <hi>walk in the Path of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly,</hi> but if he haſt not out of it, he will ſoon come to <hi>ſtand in the ways of Sinners,</hi> and, at laſt, to <hi>ſit down in the Seat of the Scornful;</hi> to mock at all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and then his Caſe is deſperate.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſufficiently caution you againſt ſo dangerous a Temptation as that of <hi>Ill Company;</hi> and eſpecially, becauſe there are ſo many Snares to draw Men into Company in general, of which the chiefeſt and (as is commonly thought) the moſt innocent is, <hi>To divert and paſs away the Time.</hi> But,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43505:8"/> O conſider what a ſad thing it is to drive away that Time which flies away too faſt. Conſider that your whole Life, if you were ſure of its duration, is but a ſhort time for to fit and prepare your Soul for an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; in which, if you ſhould miſcarry, you are for ever Wretched and Miſerable.</p>
            <p>That Word, <hi>Paſtime,</hi> is a Word of the Devil's making; the Holy Scripture ſays the direct contrary, <hi>Redeem the Time.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the difficulty of the Work you are to do, and then you will think the Time but too little. You are to become a <hi>New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> throughout, changed in every reſpect <hi>from your preſent vain Converſation:</hi> Your Immortal Spirit came pure out of God's Hand, you have here polluted it by the Vanities of the World, which are at <hi>Enmity with God;</hi> you muſt return it to Him either Innocent, (which is impoſſible) or waſh'd with the Tears of Repentance; which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance does conſiſt in a Change of your preſent Courſe, and a Turning to God. So that your Will muſt be firſt chang'd before you can be accepted of Him. You are therefore to be <hi>renewed in the Spirit of your Mind;</hi> to mortifie and ſubdue all thoſe Luſts and Affections you <hi>now</hi> ſo ſtudy to pleaſe: you are to root out that Revenge
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43505:8"/> which you <hi>Now</hi> think ſo juſtifiable upon an Affront; and to take up that Meekneſs which you <hi>Now</hi> ſo much contemn for Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice in others: you are to break off that purſuit which you <hi>Now</hi> make after Riches; and inſtead of being ſo careful for the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, you are, in the ſober Uſe of proper Means, to caſt all your Care upon God, to put your whole Truſt and Confidence in his Providence, and in all your Undertakings contentedly leave the Iſſue to Him.</p>
            <p>You are to endeavour the Change of your whole Nature; to rejoyce in Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which is <hi>Now</hi> ſo grievous: to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute liberally the Wealth you <hi>Now</hi> hoard up: to mortifie and keep under the Fleſh you <hi>Now</hi> pamper: to merit, by well-doing, the Hatred of the World, whoſe Applauſe you <hi>Now</hi> ſo much ſeek: to contemn all thoſe Pleaſures in which you <hi>Now</hi> conſume your Time: and when you have done all this, and a great deal more, there is yet a bitter Cup of Repentance behind, for all thoſe ſinful Thoughts, Words, and Actions, which, through Frailty or Wilfulneſs, you have (through the Strength of your corrupt Nature) been drawn into; and alſo for thoſe Numberleſs Sins of Omiſſion, which ſo few think of.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43505:9"/>
            <p>This Work of <hi>Repentance</hi> is ſo much the Duty of our Lives, that it is the very Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our Salvation; for by it only is Chriſt's <hi>Redemption</hi> apply'd to us; that is, He has, by his Death, made our Repentance available for the Pardon of our Sins. How inexcuſable then are we, who thus have, by God's Grace, the Means put into our Hands of qualifying our ſelves for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our Sins, and, conſequently, for Eternal Happineſs, if we ſhall fool away that Time in which this great Work muſt be done, and then think to ſet about it when <hi>Time ſhall be no more;</hi> when all Means of Reconciling our ſelves to our offended God ſhall be removed far from us?</p>
            <p>What Multitudes are there now in Hell, who ſought for <hi>Paſtime</hi> in their Youth, and thought to Repent when they grew Old? <hi>Wo! be to them that are with Child in thoſe days!</hi> (when the Days of Tribulation are come upon them) that conceive good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions; but the Days of Darkneſs over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them before they bring forth any thing. <hi>Conſider this</hi> therefore <hi>ye that forget God, lest he pluck you away, and there be none to deliver you.</hi> If you ſtop your Ear now to his Call, (and even <hi>This</hi> is one of his Calls) and are reſolved to <hi>Enjoy the Pleaſures of</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43505:9"/> 
               <hi>Sin,</hi> which are but for <hi>a Seaſon,</hi> a very ſhort Seaſon, the Time will come when <hi>you</hi> will call and cry, and then <hi>He</hi> will not hear; but then He <hi>will laugh at your Calamity, and mock when your Fear cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would you then eſcape the Terrors of that diſmal Day, that <hi>Great and Terrible Day of the Lord,</hi> the Doom of which ſhall laſt to all Eternity? Be inſtant in Prayer to God for his Aſſiſtance, to work that Change in you which I before-mentioned, and then ſet about it your ſelf with the utmoſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; loſe no Time, but <hi>Flee for thy Life,</hi> (as the Angel ſaid to <hi>LOT) and look not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee. Work out your Salvation to Day, while it is called to Day, before the Night comes, when no Man can work;</hi> for unleſs you do beget in your Mind a Love to Heavenly things while you are here, (and which cannot be done all of a ſudden) Heaven will not be Heaven to you when you come there: You will not, you cannot then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh what you have been ſo unacquainted withall, and the contrary to which you have been all along ſo uſed to and delighted with.</p>
            <p>Now one of the beſt Means to do all this is, To avoid evil Converſation, and to ſeek for Good; for, as I ſaid before, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43505:10"/> Nature of Man requires Converſation and Society: And, in a Chriſtian State, he that will travel alone in the Way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe it is narrow, will often want a hand to lift him out of the Mire of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, a Companion to ſupport him in the Storm of Perſecution, and even a Guide to admoniſh him to avoid the ruggid and rocky Ways of Imprudent Zeal, and to help him out of the Thorny Paths of a Scrupulous and Doubting Conſcience; to all which, a Chriſtian Converſation is the greateſt Help in this World.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Society is like a Bundle of Sticks laid together, one <hi>kindles</hi> another, and that <hi>Firſt</hi> even by Example; To ſee an Injured Chriſtian, Meek; a Rich one, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable; a Great one, Humble; a Mean and Ignorant one, Obedient, and Thankful for Inſtruction; an Infirm and Sickly one, Thirſting after Heaven, and looking down with Pity on the Vanities of this World; a Chriſtian can hardly be in ſuch Company without Edifying his Soul thereby.</p>
            <p>Art thou Dejected through Loſſes, or Diſappointments in thy Fortune? Lo here another much Poorer than thou, yet giving God Thanks for his Bounty to him: Art thou Tempted by Luſt? Lo here another
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43505:10"/> Chriſtian Luſtier and Stronger, who yet, by Mortification and Self-denial, by Faſting and Prayer, keeps his Soul and Body Pure, and the <hi>Fit Temple of the Holy Ghost:</hi> Art thou grovelling in the World, and <hi>eating the Bread of Carefulneſs?</hi> Lo here a Heavenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Chriſtian, <hi>having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things;</hi> that can ſay, <hi>I know how to abound, and to be in want; yea, I count all things but Dung that I may gain Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though this be a great Benefit of Chriſtian Converſation, for our Example thus to ſee in the ſame Perſon, the Chriſtian Mixtures of Greatneſs, and Humility; of Suffering, and Meekneſs; of Poverty, and Contentedneſs; of Knowledge, and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; of Pain, and Patience; which nothing could unite but that which will make the <hi>Lamb and the young Lion to lie down together;</hi> yet the Hearing of the Ear in this is yet of more Benefit than the Seeing with the Eye.</p>
            <p>Indeed the ſilent Arguments of Example work even upon the Natural Man; but Diſcourſe edifies more the Chriſtian by <hi>Grace;</hi> for <hi>Faith comes by Hearing.</hi> And therefore, in the <hi>Second</hi> place, one Chriſtian <hi>kindles</hi> another by Conſolation, Counſel, Admonition, Inſtruction, and <hi>Reproof,</hi> which, though it be every ones Duty to do,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43505:11"/> yet none performs it but the true Chriſtian; he who has a greater Love for other Mens Souls, than for their Favour or Eſteem. For want of the Diſcharge of this one Duty alone, How many Thouſand well-diſpoſed Perſons are utterly loſt? who cannot of themſelves ſee <hi>the Sin that does ſo eaſily beſet them:</hi> Witneſs <hi>David,</hi> who could not ſee whilſt himſelf was Party, and lived near a Year inſenſibly under the Guilt of <hi>Murther</hi> and <hi>Adultery.</hi> Certainly Miſerable is the Man that has no ſuch Friend, and none can be ſuch a Friend but the Chriſtian; for, he that does not <hi>cast the Beam out of his own Eye,</hi> before he pretends to <hi>take the Mote out of his Neighbours,</hi> his Reproof will be taken for Envy or ill Nature, and ſo will Exaſperate rather than Melt.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> this Chriſtian Converſation might be yet more highly improv'd, and render'd much more beneficial to our Souls, if we would, in converſing together, ſo ſeriouſly conſider the the Graces we want, and the Bleſſings we injoy, as by God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Prayer and Praiſe, and the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Word, to bring Chriſt into our Company, to have Him in the midſt of us, O how happy would that Meeting be! (and even this we have his ſure Word of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43505:11"/> Promiſe for;) then would our Meetings be every Day for the Better to us, and we ſhould rejoyce to come often together, and even injoy that Communion of Saints which we hope to be of in Heaven. A Zeal for God's Glory, a Thirſt for his Ordinances, a tender Love and Pity to the Souls of Men, and a Strictneſs of Life, would <hi>then</hi> inſenſibly grow upon us, ſo that we ſhould be <hi>habitually</hi> prepared for all Holy Duties, for the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Lord's-Supper, and even for a ſudden Departure out of this World, if it ſhould pleaſe God ſo to call us hence; and might hope to be reckoned of the Number of thoſe of whom the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> ſpeaks, ſaying, <hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkened and heard it, and a Book of Remembrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and thought upon his Name. And they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in that day when I make up my Jewels, and I will ſpare them as a Man ſpareth his own Son that ſerveth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are thoſe that would count you Troubleſome, and Buſie-bodies, to give <hi>them</hi> Advice, or to pretend to concern your ſelves about their Souls; but, however, let
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43505:12"/> not this diſcourage you; for, of thoſe you give Advice to, or admoniſh, if but <hi>One</hi> in <hi>Twenty</hi> hears you ſeriouſly, you have no reaſon to repent the Loſs of your Labour in all the reſt: Nay, if even that it ſelf ſhould not happen, yet for Religion's ſake you ſhould not hold your Peace; for, Shall Men be Impudent in the Devil's Service, and ſhall we be Aſhamed to own God's? Is the Great God and our Maker become ſo inconſiderable in our Eſteem, that we dare not ſtand by Him, when Men dare ſtand up for their Vices? Is Eternal Salvation ſo indifferent a thing, that we ſhould be uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for it? Do we ſee the Vices of the Age Growing and Spreading, and ſhall not we ſtand in Oppoſition to them? Therefore, ſince one teaches another Vice, let us teach each other Virtue; ſince one guides ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Hell, let us help one another for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the Way to Heaven; and as they make one another Prophane, let us teach one another Righteouſneſs in all our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> and <hi>Friendly Societies;</hi> and let us incourage others to do the ſame by our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Example, that <hi>Religion</hi> may once more become a general Practice; that our Churches may be fuller, and the Publick Prayers more frequented by all that are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43505:12"/> true Members thereof; and thoſe <hi>that name the Name of Chriſt may depart from Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if it be Charity to direct the Blind in his Way, or when we ſee our Neighbour in danger of being Robbed, or his Houſe in danger of being Burnt, if to run and help him is Charity; then certainly it is greater Charity to inſtruct the Ignorant, by ſhewing them the right way to <hi>Salvation.</hi> And therefore, if you ſee your Chriſtian Brother, your Neighbour or Fellow-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, in danger of being Ruin'd by keeping ill Company, or their Souls in danger of Hell-Fire by Prophaning the Lord's-Day, by Neglecting his Laws, and Forſaking his Commandments, to help ſuch, by Godly Advice and Admonition, is a great Deed of Charity; nay, it is your Duty too; for thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Levit. 19. 17. Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy Heart: Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer Sin upon him.</hi> Be not Guilty then of this great Crime upon any Pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; <hi>But Exhort one another daily, while it is called to day, lest any of you be hardened through the Deceitfulneſs of Sin; knowing that he that converteth a Sinner from the Error of his Ways, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death, and ſhall cover a multitude of Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43505:13"/>
            <p>All the Texts almoſt of the Holy Scripture point to this Duty, either by Exhorting or Commanding us to ſet about this Neceſſary Work, firſt to lead good Lives our ſelves, and then to incourage others to do the ſame. I do not exhort you to Controverſie, nor to meddle much with thoſe of another Perſuaſion, for that is the Miniſter's Work; but this is your <hi>One thing needful,</hi> to meddle with thoſe that own the ſame Church, and profeſs the ſame Faith, and yet act contrary to it in their Lives and Converſations. Put <hi>theſe</hi> in mind of their Baptiſmal Vow; How they then promiſed to renounce the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, and yet do live within the Embraces of them all. Ask them, How they dare blame others for their Unbelief, while they live like Atheiſts themſelves? How they dare condemn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for ſeparating from the Church, when their own Lives and Converſations are quite contrary to the Holy Doctrines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? How they dare reproach others for want of Seriouſneſs, when they live looſe Lives themſelves: and are ſo far from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring their Creator in the Days of their Youth, that they forget Him and his Laws all their Days? But intreat them to take the Wiſe Man's Counſel, That they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43505:13"/> 
               <hi>make no tarrying to turn to the Lord, and put it not off from day to day.</hi> Put them in mind of the great Benefit of a Holy Life and early Piety, and what a Pleaſure it will be when they come to die, to look back upon a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent Life, and be able to ſay with <hi>Hezekiah</hi> upon a Death-Bed, <hi>Remember now, O Lord, how I have walked before thee in Truth, and with a perfect Heart, and have done that which was right in thine Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you that have already taſted thoſe Joys which ariſe from a good Conſcience, and the Pleaſures of a Godly Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, <hi>fall not from your own Stedfaſtneſs;</hi> and ſince you ſee Wicked Men take ſuch Pains to ſerve their Luſts, to pleaſe their Senſes, and gratifie their Appetites, be you at ſome Pains alſo to ſerve your God, to advance his Glory, yea, and to encourage others likewiſe to do the ſame. And if there be but <hi>Two</hi> in a Street that intend really to ſerve God, to frequent the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Prayers of the Church, let them make it their Buſineſs to perſwade Two more to do the ſame, and let your Prayers be frequent and fervent to God, that He would increaſe the Number of true Believers, and that it would pleaſe Him to bring into the Way of Truth, all ſuch as have erred and are deceived.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43505:14"/>
            <p>This would be one great Means to mend the World, and without this it will hardly be done; it is not good Books, nor good Preaching, that will reclaim a Prophane and Profligate Wretch; for ſuch Perſons will neither read good Books, nor hear Sermons; they are out of the reach of all other Methods, except Counſel, Advice, and Exhortation, and oftentimes they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe that too. But when good Men are as Bold as evil Men are Impudent, and as openly Good as others are Bad; when Piety has Authority in it, and frowns Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs out of Countenance, then the World will mend; and if not grow Devout, yet at leaſt, grow Modeſter and Civiller to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Religion, when Virtuous Men give good Evidence that they do believe in good Earneſt, by endeavouring the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all vicious and open Offenders, as the Law directs.</p>
            <p>And altho <hi>Piety</hi> is now-a-days laugh'd at, and <hi>Religion</hi> out of Faſhion, yet (that I may now ſhew you how to Practiſe what I have been hitherto Recommending, (I mean a <hi>Chriſtian Converſation and Society)</hi> I muſt tell you, that there are ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in this Barren Age, and thoſe of conſiderable Rank and Quality, who think
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43505:14"/> it is ſo far from unbecoming them, that nothing is more acceptable to them than Pious Diſcourſe, and the Company of ſuch Men as endeavour to make the Word of God their Rule to walk by.</p>
            <p>And I have both known &amp; heard of ſome Numbers of Religious Men in this City, who Meet at one anothers Houſes, uſually every Week, or as often as Occaſions permit, and there make it their Buſineſs to inforce upon one anothers Minds the great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtianity; to live up to the Doctrines of our Church; to frequent the Holy Sacrament every Lord's-Day; and the Publick Prayers every Day; they having a quick ſenſe of Piety, and a great concern upon them for another World; they endeavour to preſerve this Temper in themſelves, and to propagate it to others; and many good <hi>Rules</hi> they have among them; and by their frequent <hi>Meetings</hi> they take Notice of each others Virtues, and ſo they ſtrive to imitate each other. In one, there abounds the Grace of Meekneſs; in another, is a great Chriſtian Courage and Zeal to ſtand up for God's Glory; in another, Patience; in another, Self-denial and Mortification; in another, a Zeal for Peace-making; and this makes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43505:15"/> them the more to deſire each other's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as being Monitors to one another by their Example. And this is one of their Rules, <hi>Never to ſpeak Ill of one another;</hi> and if, at any time, they hear Ill of one another, or of any other good Chriſtian, they firſt go and ſee if it be true what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Men do report of him, rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that as one Man may <hi>do</hi> amiſs, ſo may another more eaſily <hi>ſpeak</hi> amiſs, that being <hi>the Sin that does ſo eaſily beſet</hi> every Man: and alſo, that as Society is the Excellency and great Bleſſing of Mankind, ſo Slander and Reproach, Cenſuring and Evil-ſpeaking, poyſons and deſtroys all Love and Charity in the World: But if it prove true that ſuch an one <hi>has been overtaken in a Fault,</hi> they take the Apoſtle's Advice, and <hi>reſtore him in the Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering themſelves alſo may be Tempted.</p>
            <p>At theſe Meetings there is no Diſcourſe of News, nor Trade, nor Worldly Buſineſs, or Controverſie in Religion; but they take care that all their <hi>Speech be ſeaſon'd with Grace, and to the uſe of Edifying, and may miniſter Grace to the Hearers:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they apply themſelves to the conſtant Reading and Studying of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that <hi>the Word of Christ may dwell</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43505:15"/> 
               <hi>richly in them, that ſo out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth may ſpeak.</hi> They do often, at theſe times, confer about the State of their Souls: they do examine into the Growth and Decay of Piety in general, and alſo particularly among themſelves; and each ſhews what does moſt affect and influence <hi>him;</hi> and every one does frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inculcate and ſtir up to Perfection.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that were <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and had Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, made it <hi>their</hi> Buſineſs to order their <hi>Converſation ſo as to adorn the Goſpel,</hi> and publickly to diſcountenance Vice, by the Promoting the Making of good Laws, and the Putting of them in Execution, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their Example was neceſſary to influence Trades-Men to be Sober, to be Religious, and to be Juſt in all their Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to imitate <hi>their Burning</hi> and <hi>Shining Lights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that were <hi>Maſters of Families</hi> acted in their Stations like Men that believed in good earneſt that there was a Judgment to come, a Heaven and a Hell; and that God would call all Men to an Account, what Good they have done in their Generation. This made them never to omit going to Prayers in their Families, and telling their Children and Servants what a Benefit it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43505:16"/> will be to them to live in the Fear of God, and ſerve Him in their tender Years.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that were <hi>Officers</hi> in the Pariſhes they lived in, would ſuffer no Diſorder in the Streets, nor no Night-Walker, no Drunkard, no Swearer, no Prophaner of the Lord's Day, to go Unpuniſhed: And this was one end of joyning themſelves into <hi>Neighbourly Societies,</hi> to conſult upon Methods whereby to put a ſtop to Vice, and bring Men to a Sence of their Duty to God and Man: And thus they acted like Honeſt Men in their <hi>Offices,</hi> without Bribes, or Feaſting upon the Pariſh Charge.</p>
            <p>There was likewiſe another Sort of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Societies,</hi> and thoſe were of <hi>Young-Men,</hi> that were <hi>Apprentices, Servants,</hi> and <hi>Journy-Men;</hi> and theſe ſtrived to out-do the reſt in Zeal and Piety; being not engaged in the World, they endeavour to Dedicate themſelves to God in their tender Years. To this end they joyned themſelves into <hi>Societies,</hi> and there met once a Week, perhaps in ſome Upper Room, to excite and ſtir up one another to avoid the Sins of the Age they liv'd in, and to imprint likewiſe upon other Mens Minds a Sence of Religion; to this end they ſet up, on the Lord's-Day, Sermons at Night, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43505:16"/> the Sacrament in the Morning, and the Prayers every Night in the Week in divers Churches, that they might have Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to go without waſting their Maſters time; (and Inſtructed, at their own Charge, many poor Children in reading <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and in the Grounds of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion)</hi> and where there was but one or two ſuch in a Street, they made it their Buſineſs to get two more to do the ſame, ſo much was every one concerned for his Brother's Soul; and where they ſaw a Young Man in their Neighbourhood that had no Sence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but lived in Neglect of it, they ſtrove to reclaim him, and ſo did increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>True Believers,</hi> and make the publick Prayers more frequented; and this makes Religion revive again, and come ſomething toward its Primitive Inſtitution. I have been but too ſhort in giving you an Account of thoſe Men, conſidering what other good Works they have done for our Example, whom we have great Reaſon to imitate, as you may ſee in the Reverend Mr. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>'s Book of the <hi>Riſe and Progreſs of the Religious Societies;</hi> as alſo in another Book, Entituled, <hi>An Account of the Societies for Reformation of Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43505:17"/>
            <p>And though you have perhaps ſeen or heard, that ſome few who have thus <hi>begun in the Spirit, have ended in the Fleſh;</hi> yet let not this diſcourage you; <hi>for he that endures to the End ſhall be ſaved:</hi> but take our Saviour's Advice; for He tells us in St. <hi>Luke, That no Man having ſet his hand to the Plough, and looking back, is fit for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> And therefore, as you have begun by your Baptiſmal Vow, and by the Chriſtian Profeſſion you have ſince made, endeavour to go on from Vertue to Vertue. And you that have found the Comfort of leading a good Life, the Joy and Pleaſure of a good Conſcience, the Advantage and Benefit of frequenting the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the publick Service of the Church: You that now ſee the Odiouſneſs of thoſe Vices that others wallow in: That ſee the Beauty of that Vertue which others deſpiſe, and the Charms of that Grace that others laugh at: You that ſee the Reaſonableneſs of Chriſt's Precepts, which others count an intollerable Yoke: In a word, You that have ſome Sence and Hopes of another World, while Thouſands live as if there were none; O let not theſe Comforts be hid within your Breaſts; but knowing <hi>your ſelves Converted, ſtrengthen</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43505:17"/> 
               <hi>your Brethren,</hi> as is commanded by our Saviour in St. <hi>Luke;</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> tells us, <hi>To know the Art of Alms, is greater than to be Crown'd with the Diadem of Kings;</hi> and yet, <hi>To convert one Soul, is greater than to pour out Ten Thouſand Talents into the Basket of the Poor;</hi> therefore, according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Advice, <hi>Warn them that are unruly, Comfort the feeble-minded, Support the weak, be Patient towards all Men; ſee that none render Evil for Evil to any Man; but ever follow that which is good, both among your ſelves, and to all Men;</hi> and if you be laugh'd at for your pains, conſider, that <hi>Bleſſed are they who ſhall be reviled for Chriſt's ſake.</hi> You may poſſibly caſt <hi>your Pearl before Swine;</hi> but let them know, that mock at Religion and Piety, what a ſad after-Reckoning <hi>They</hi> ſhall have, when <hi>the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be ſet, and the Books opened,</hi> as in the Fifth Chapter of <hi>Wiſdom, Then ſhall the Righteous Man ſtand in great Boldneſs, before the Face of ſuch as have afflicted him, and made no account of his Labours. When they ſee it, they ſhall be troubled with a terrible Fear, and ſhall be amazed at the ſtrangeneſs of his Salvation, ſo far beyond all they look'd for. Then they repenting, and groaning for Anguiſh, ſhall ſay within themſelves, This was</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43505:18"/> 
               <hi>he whom we have had ſometimes in Deriſion,</hi> and a Proverb of Reproach. <hi>We Fools counted his Life Madneſs, and his End to be without Honour. How is he numbred among the Children of God, and his Lot is among the Saints! Then in ſorrow and grief of Heart ſhall they cry out upon themſelves; What hath Pride profited us? or, What good hath Riches with our vaunting brought us? All thoſe things are vaniſhed like a Shadow, and as a Post that paſſeth by; but the Righteous live for evermore, their Reward is alſo with the most Highest.</hi> Warn them therefore by theſe <hi>Terrors of the Lord,</hi> that they <hi>ſtand in awe and ſin not;</hi> but that they <hi>Die unto Sin, and Live unto Righteouſneſs.</hi> Intreat them to conſecrate the Morning, the Youth of their Age to God; and that they think it not enough to give Him the ſleepieſt Hours of the Day, while they beſtow the livelieſt upon the World: nor to Sin as long as they can, and then turn to God. For, How many, alas! have been cut off in this fooliſh Stupidity, and know not by how ſmall a Thread the Sword of Juſtice hangs over their Heads? for though God is Merciful, yet it is only to the Penitent; but he is alſo Juſt, and <hi>rewards every Man according to his works.</hi> He hath Magazines
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43505:18"/> of Vengeance, Store-Houſes of Curſes, and can ruine a ſinful Creature a thouſand ways; and yet, How Merry, notwithſtanding all this, is the <hi>Drunkard</hi> over his Cups? And how boldly does the <hi>Swearer</hi> ſend up his dreadful Oaths to Heaven? and all this, becauſe God is Merciful and Long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But, O let them know what a terrible Abuſe it is, to let God's Mercy provoke them to Wantonneſs, and his Patience to cauſe Sin to live in their Souls; that his Goodneſs ſhould tempt them to be Fooliſh, and his Compaſſion prompt them to affront his Glory; that his Kindneſs ſhould prove their Bane, and that the Meat he gives them ſhould increaſe their Corruption; that his Corn and Wine ſhould be turn'd into Contempt of his Majeſty, and that they ſhould make uſe of the Eaſe he gives them to Fight againſt his Laws; that the Plenty they enjoy by his Providence, ſhould encourage them to make War with Him, from whom all their Plenty flows. O what monſtrous Provocations are theſe! If their Children or Servants ſhould uſe <hi>Them</hi> ſo, what Puniſhments could they think too great for them? And muſt God put up Affronts which they will not? O bid them conſider how He waits for their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43505:19"/> Repentance, and invites them to it; <hi>Turn ye, turn ye,</hi> ſaith the Lord your God, <hi>Why will ye die?</hi> and yet they fruſtrate his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency. He is Patient, and would have them prevent the Blow; and yet they are ready to pluck it down on their heads. To ſuch the Apoſtle ſpeaks thus, <hi>Rom. 2. 1. Therefore thou art unexeuſable, O Man, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou art, that deſpiſest the Riches of his Goodneſs, and Forbearance, and Long-ſuffering, not conſidering that the Goodneſs of God leads to Repentance.</hi> Make them ſenſible therefore of the Benefit of Subduing their Luſts and Paſſions: Beg of them to reſtrain their inordinate Deſires, and their ſenſual Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites; to curb their Anger, and to put away all Hatred toward their Fellow-Chriſtians; to root out their Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; to advance in Charity toward their Neighbours; to grow Eminent in the Love of God; to keep Holy the Lord's-Day; to honour his Name, and obey his Laws. Put them in mind to come to the Publick Prayers of the Church, and tell them, that in the Publick Solemnities God opens his Treaſures, and pours out his Grace more abundantly upon them. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotions, and the ſecret Offices of Religion, are like the Refreſhing of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43505:19"/> with the diſtilling and petty Drops of a Water-Pot; but the Returns to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes made in the Temple, and Services offer'd up in the publick Communion of Saints, is like Rain from Heaven. Adviſe them to behave themſelves decently in the Houſe of God; for to be rude and talking, to laugh and gaze about, or to do any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decency in that Place, is to affront the Almighty to his very Face: And for their more devout Behaviour in the Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to them to read Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s <hi>Companion to the Temple;</hi> and another thing put them in mind of, not to repeat the <hi>Abſolution,</hi> for that is to be pronounced by the Prieſt alone; and this I urge, becauſe I have obſerv'd ſome ſaying the Abſolution along after the Prieſt, as if we could pardon our ſelves: nor to repeat the <hi>Commandments</hi> in the Church; but we ought to hearken to them with Reverence, as if they were then ſpoken from God: neither ſhould they repeat any of the <hi>Prayers</hi> with an audible Voice, except the <hi>Lord's-Prayer</hi> and the <hi>Reſponſes,</hi> becauſe they give great Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to others in their Devotions.</p>
            <p>And I would particularly recommend to every one, to buy and acquaint themſelves with <hi>the Thirty Nine Articles of the Church</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43505:20"/> 
               <hi>of</hi> England, that they may lay a good Foundation, and have ſolid Principles to go by: I am afraid that ſome that think very well of themſelves, do not rightly underſtand the Principles of their Religion. Theſe <hi>Articles</hi> are as Sea-Marks, to ſhew what Rocks and Sands you are to avoid; and by being well acquainted with them, you will be able to give a good Account of the Doctrinal Part of our Religion; and this is an excellent Foundation to build the Practical Part upon.</p>
            <p>And of all things, let me warn you that you do not, in any Religious Converſation or Society, or elſewhere, ſay or do any thing to the Diſparagement of the <hi>Miniſtry of the Church of</hi> England, but ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a due Reſpect for that Order: In all greater Difficulties reſort to them, and pay them that Obedience and Honour which the Holy Ghoſt requires of you. And though there may be ſome bad Men among them, yet learn to diſtinguiſh the Order from the Defects that cleave to ſome of them; and for all the ill Lives or Weakneſs of ſome, do not condemn the reſt, nor erect your ſelves into Teachers; but, with great Humility, edifie and encourage one another in Duties and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43505:20"/> Virtues, which belong to all Chriſtians. Pride &amp; Self-conceitedneſs will ruine your Religion; and if Order and Decency be not preſerved, your Meeting will become a Riot, not a Chriſtian Society. Nothing will adorn your Piety more than a due Submiſſion to your Paſtors; and thoſe that would entice you to deſpiſe <hi>Them,</hi> are certainly not your Friends, but Enemies: Therefore take the Apoſtle's Advice, <hi>Heb. 13. 17. Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves: for they watch for your Souls, as they that must give account: that they may do it with Joy, and not with Grief: for that is unprofitable for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND now, in the laſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>This following Part being took out of a private Letter a friend of mine deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>I thought it might not be amiſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to you here.</hi>
               </note> place, there is one thing more that I would particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to you that are <hi>Maſters of Families;</hi> which is this, That you would make Conſcience of going to <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> with your <hi>Families</hi> at leaſt <hi>once</hi> or <hi>twice</hi> a <hi>day;</hi> a Duty I think we may trace from our Father <hi>Adam;</hi> for he was no ſooner fallen from his Innocence, and a Happy State,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43505:21"/> but was ſenſible <hi>God</hi> was Angry with him; and he thought it neceſſary to implore the Offended Deity by <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Invocation,</hi> by <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Repentance, Offerings</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices;</hi> and inſtructs his Children in the Knowledge of <hi>Divine things,</hi> and maintains <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Worſhip of God</hi> in his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily:</hi> For we find <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> bringing their <hi>Oblations;</hi> and <hi>Seth</hi> and <hi>Enos</hi> called upon the Name of the Lord; and <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> walked with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 4. 5. 26. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 9.</p>
            <p>It cannot be doubted but that the Holy <hi>Patriarchs</hi> were careful in this Duty, as appears by that Character God gave of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Gen. 18. 19. I know him that he will command his Children and his Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold after him; and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord to do Juſtice and Judgment:</hi> to which they joyned Prayers and Praiſes, as a neceſſary Duty: And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening, and at Noon will I Pray;</hi> and you know <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Reſolution in this Duty, <hi>but as for me and my Houſe, we will ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſhua 24. 15.</p>
            <p>Theſe Men did not comply with the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Neglect of the Times: And, indeed, it's no thanks to be Religious, or go to Prayer with your Family, when it is the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43505:21"/> Humour and Faſhion of the Times; for then you would be aſham'd to neglect it, by reaſon others do it: The greateſt Trial is, as it was with <hi>Noah,</hi> when we live in the midſt of a corrupt Generation; for it is the Crown of Vertue to be Good, when there are all manner of Temptations to the contrary, when the greateſt part of Men go the other way, when Vertue and Honeſty are laugh'd at, and cenſur'd as an over-wiſe and affected Singularity. Thus it was with <hi>Noah,</hi> he contended with the Vices of the Age, and dared to own God and Religion in his Family, when almoſt all Mankind, beſides himſelf and his Family, had rejected and thrown it off.</p>
            <p>And although Maſters of Families are ſo careleſs of this Duty, now it's grown out of Faſhion, yet it is a Duty ſtill. The <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> did Pray with their Families three times a Day, and looked on't as a great Sin to omit it; and, What can we expect from you who do not care to Worſhip God at all! Our bare being of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> or calling our ſelves Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> will avail but little without this Duty; and our Saviour hath intimated ſo much unto us in the <hi>Lord's-Prayer,</hi> by teaching
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43505:22"/> us to Pray for our <hi>Daily Bread;</hi> and I need not tell you that you have Daily Wants to be ſupply'd; Wants for your ſelves, and Wants for your Children and Servants: Have you not Daily Infirmities both in your Self and Family to be healed? Are you not Daily ſubject to Dangers and Temptations? And do you not Daily Sin againſt God? And is it not neceſſary then that you Daily Pray unto God for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of all your Wants? for the Healing of all your Infirmities? for the Preventing the Danger you are Daily ſubject to? for the Strengthning you againſt all your Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations? for the Pardoning of all your Sins? Surely your Daily Wants, your Daily Infirmities, Daily Dangers, your Daily Temptations, and your Daily Sins, do all call upon you for your Daily Prayers in your Family: For your being a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that <hi>Church,</hi> I am ſure will not excuſe the Neglect thereof.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this I may be bold to affirm, That there is no <hi>Church</hi> this Day in the Chriſtian World, that, in her Doctrine, doth encourage real Goodneſs more, or ſtrive more to keep the Ballance even, that God may have the things that are God's, and Man the things that are Man's, than
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43505:22"/> the <hi>Church</hi> we now live in: And how you will vindicate your ſelf in the laſt day for this Neglect, I cannot tell: When you are exhorted in the Church, told in the Pulpit that it is your Duty, and God threatens the Neglect thereof with not owning you at the laſt Day, if you do not Pray with your Family at Home, as well as bring them to Church. Why will you profeſs your ſelf Her Member, if you will not obey Her Doctrine? What do you go to Church for, only to drive away the time, or to act the part of a Hypocrite? Do you think the Miniſter is ſent to Preach to you in Vain? If you think he doth not Preach the Truth, why will you go to Hear him? If he doth Preach the Truth, why will you not ſet about to Practice what he ſaith? Do you think that God takes no notice of the Neglect? or that He will not call you to an Account for it? Yes, yes, God takes Notice of you, as He ſaid to the <hi>Prophet, They came before thee as my People, and they hear my Words, but will not keep them;</hi> and what our Saviour ſaith, in <hi>Luke 19. 27. to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable Servant,</hi> may be ſaid here; <hi>But thoſe mine Enemies which would not that I ſhould Reign over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43505:23"/> 
               <hi>me.</hi> Men perhaps cannot ſee this Neglect, but God and Angels ſee it; yes, and Devils too, which will all be Witneſſes againſt you in the laſt Day of Account. O how will you wiſh, when you come to Die, you had performed this Duty more your ſelf, inſtead of Laughing at thoſe that do it; as too often I have heard ſome Men blame the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> for their uſing <hi>Extemporè Prayers</hi> in their <hi>Families,</hi> when they themſelves uſe none at all in theirs; and think their bare being a Member of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and going to <hi>Church</hi> once a Week, is a ſufficient Service for Almighty God. If I am not miſtaken, this has been your Fault, <hi>Brother;</hi> And will not this be an Argument againſt you in the laſt Day? And will not their uſing <hi>Extemporè</hi> Prayers in their Family, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you for uſing none at all in yours? For while you condemn all thoſe that are of another Perſwaſion, who are only Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken or Miſled in ſome Texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or falſe Notions of other Mens, you condemn your own Neglect; and this all Men will allow, That he that is Miſled in matter of Judgment, is more to be excuſed than that Man who lives contrary to a known Command; for the laſt is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43505:23"/> in his own Judgment, if he will but take time to conſider it.</p>
            <p>And let me tell you, <hi>Brother,</hi> you will find it a very beneficial and very eaſie Duty, when Love ingageth the Practice of it: for, What can there be more eaſie than to pray to God, and to repreſent our Needs; and that we have our Needs ſupplyed only for asking and deſiring paſſionately and humbly? Can we buy any thing cheaper than at the rate of an Humble Prayer? Conſider how many excellent Promiſes are made to Prayer; and that nothing diſpoſes us more to receive the Grace of God, and a Bleſſing upon our Family, than Prayer: What can be more pleaſant than this Duty of Prayer? when Chriſt unites them to his own, and bids us come for Relief and Pardon of our Sins: For Prayer can open the Gates of Heaven, and ſhut the Gates of Hell; it can open the Treaſures of Rain, and ſoften the Iron Rocks till they melt into Tears: It is an Act of Grace, and the higheſt Honour that we Duſt and Aſhes are admitted to ſpeak to the Eternal God, to run to Him as to a Father, to complain of our Burthens, to explicate our Scruples, to beg Remedy and Eaſe, Support and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43505:24"/> Comfort, Health and Safety, Counſel and Salvation.</p>
            <p>And what can be more unreaſonable than to neglect this Duty, upon which ſo many and ſo great Bleſſings, both upon your ſelf and Family, do depend? How Unkind are you to your ſelf, and not only ſo, but Unkind to all that are about you? I mean, Unkind to their Souls, and extreamly Uncharitable, to take no care at all of this Duty; for the Neglect of which God often ſends great Judgments upon a whole Family, either by ſore <note place="margin">Jer. 10. 25.</note> Affliction, or ſometimes, which is worſe, <hi>Hardneſs and Blindneſs of Heart;</hi> for the Word of God will certainly be fulfilled; he hath ſaid, <hi>That the Houſe of the Wicked ſhall be overthrown,</hi> Prov. 14. 11. And may not that be ſaid to be a Wicked Houſe, when neither Thou, nor thy Wife, (which ſhould be Lights to the reſt) nor Children, nor Servants, make Conſcience of this Duty, to Worſhip God by Prayer? or if you or they chance to do it when you are in the Bed, it is with that Coldneſs and Sleepineſs, that I may call it <hi>none at all,</hi> or at leaſt Lip-Service, when the Heart is a Sleep; and by your Example, perhaps your Children and Servants think it not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43505:24"/> their Duty to go to Prayers at all, neither Night nor Morning; and ſo they go to Bed, and riſe the next Morning, like <hi>Brutes,</hi> without Calling upon that God, <hi>in whom we Live, and Move, and have our Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let me intreat you to take courage, to ſet about this Duty your ſelf, that you may not have Sins of others to anſwer for, as well as your own; take up that brave Reſolution of the Prophet <hi>Joſhua; But as for me and my Houſe, we will Serve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As you are a <hi>Maſter of a Family,</hi> you have a place of <hi>Trust</hi> committed to you by <hi>God,</hi> who will certainly call you to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for it: For here you are commanded by God to act the part of a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>Priest,</hi> and a <hi>Judge,</hi> over your little <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth;</hi> the Fourth Commandment tells you, that every Maſter of a Family muſt take care of his Sons and Daughters, his Man-ſervants and Maid-ſervants, and All within his Gates; not only to provide Food and Raiment for them, but to take care of their Souls, which is the better part: And here you are to act for God, you have the Charge from Him, not only of Bodies, but of Souls; therefore let not the Dignity of your place make you forget your Duty;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43505:25"/> for God will certainly call you and me to an Account, for what Good we have done in our Generations, and how far we have ſought his Glory; and although I have only inſiſted upon your going to <hi>Prayers with your Family,</hi> yet that is not all you are to do, only I am in hopes if you would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that, you could not eaſily neglect the other Duties; ſuch as <hi>Reading the Word of God, Singing of Pſalms, Catechiſing,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing</hi> your <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> in <hi>True Chriſtian Virtues,</hi> and ſhowing them their <hi>Duty to God and Man;</hi> to ſee if they <hi>thrive in Grace,</hi> or make Conſcience of their <hi>Duty</hi> to <hi>God</hi> as well as to your <hi>Self:</hi> For I fear we ſhall have but little aſſurance of our own Salvation, except we endeavour the Reformation of our whole Houſe, ſo far as lieth in our power: The mark of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Goodneſs was, <hi>That he would command his Children and his Houſhold after him:</hi> And <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>101ſt Pſalm,</hi> declares his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to this Duty: And Good Men in all Ages have carefully performed it; and the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> were very ſtrict in it. And can we think to go to Heaven a nearer way, when our Saviour hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all Men to perform it? The Scripture condemns all thoſe that neglect
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43505:25"/> it; for if we be aſham'd to own Chriſt in our Families, and deny the Worſhip and Service that is due to Him here, He will deny us before his Father, and all his Saints and Angels, at the laſt Day; and then, How ſad will our Condition be!</p>
            <p>But I hope, <hi>Dear Brother,</hi> I may take it for granted, that you will neglect it no longer: For conſider how great ſatisfaction it will be to you when you come to Die, that you have laid up a good Foundation for the time to come, a Treaſure that no Devil can rob you of; a good Conſcience then that you have diſcharged your Duty, will go further than Purſes of Gold. O the Pleaſure of looking back upon a well-ſpent Life in God's Service, and Reforming our Families to the beſt of our Powers! Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee how charming it makes Death, and how it doth ſupport us in our Sickneſs; arms us to bear the Pangs of Death through the Merits of Chriſt, and makes us die with Joy, with Hope, with Comfort and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore let me intreat you once more, to take up that brave Reſolution of the Prophet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Joſhua, But as for me and my Houſe, we will Serve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, in the laſt place, let me adviſe you, in the words of St. <hi>James,</hi> chap. 5. v. 13.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43505:26"/> 
               <hi>Is any among you Afflicted? let him Pray. Is any Merry? let him ſing Pſalms.</hi> And avoid all vicious and prophane <hi>Songs,</hi> which corrupt the Mind; Singing nothing but <hi>Pſalms, Hymns, and Divine Songs,</hi> which will raiſe the Mind to a Heavenly Frame; a Duty ſo practis'd by the Chriſtians of old, that St. <hi>Hierom</hi> relates of the Place where he Lived, <hi>That you could not go into the Field, but you might hear the Ploughman at his Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalujahs, the Mower at his Hymns, and the Vine-Dreſſer Singing</hi> David'<hi>s Pſalms:</hi> So careful were they to follow the Apoſtle's Advice in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 19. (with which I ſhall conclude) <hi>Speaking to your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, Singing and making Melody in your Hearts to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>That you may be Stedfaſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmovable, always abounding in the Works of the LORD,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Is the Hearty Prayer of Your Loving Brother, <hi>S. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:43505:26"/>
            <head>THE RULES AND ORDERS OF A SOCIETY.</head>
            <p n="1">I. THat the ſole Deſign of this <hi>Society</hi> being to promote real Holineſs of Heart and Life, it is abſolutely neceſſary, That no Perſon ſhould be admitted into this <hi>Society</hi> as a <hi>Member,</hi> but ſuch as are well known to ſome of the <hi>Society,</hi> as to their Lives and Converſations, and that they are of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as now Eſtabliſht, and that they are frequent Communicants of the Lord's-Supper, and ſuch as do endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make themſelves <hi>Wiſe unto Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Every <hi>Member</hi> ſhall meet (if he can conveniently) about Six of the Clock at the Place of Meeting, one Night in every Week, in order to incourage each other in Practical Holineſs.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That at theſe Meetings no Perſon ſhall diſcourſe of State-Affairs, nor in the way of Trade, nor any hot Controverſial
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43505:27"/> points in Religion or Government; but that the whole drift of our Diſcourſe be to glorifie God, and edifie one another in Love.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. There ſhall be <hi>Two Stewards</hi> choſen, by the majority of Voices, once every Year, or oftner, who ſhall receive all Weekly Contributions, and other Charities which ſhall come to the Diſpoſal of this <hi>Society:</hi> And that on the Day of their going out they ſhall give an Account of their Receivings and Disburſements, and pay in the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus to their Succeſſours; and no Money ſhall be paid by them to any Charitable Uſes, or others, but what ſhall be firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and agreed upon by the <hi>Society</hi> at a Meeting. And each <hi>Member</hi> ſhall give at their Entrance, and a Regiſter ſhall be kept of Receipts and Diſtributions.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Every <hi>Member</hi> of this <hi>Society</hi> ſhall pay a Week towards the Charge of our Meeting, in <hi>Chamber-Rent, Candles, &amp;c.</hi> and for Charitable Uſes, if there be any Overplus; and Spiritual Charity is the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be recommended.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. If any Perſon of this <hi>Society</hi> ſhall fall into any ſcandalous Sin, that the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> having well inform'd themſelves thereof, ſhall exclude him from any further
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43505:27"/> Aſſembling with them till he ſhall give publick Teſtimony of his Repentance.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. At <hi>Whitſontide</hi> or <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> there ſtall be a ſmall Love-Feaſt, by the Conſent of the whole, or major-part of the <hi>Society,</hi> with few Varieties, and at an eaſie Charge, to be defrayed by every <hi>Members</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing proportionably.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. That if the major-part thinks proper, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Pariſh for the time being ſhall be <hi>Preſident</hi> of this <hi>Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. At their Meeting they ſhall obſerve this Method: Aſſoon as ſome of the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> are come, if the <hi>Stewards,</hi> or either of them be there, he ſhall take the <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> and after ſaying the Prayer for the <hi>ſecond Sunday</hi> in <hi>Advent,</hi> ſhall read a Chapter; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, any one that thinks fit may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereon, either by Explaining, for the Edification of others; or by asking Queſtions, for his own Information; or diſcourſing of any other Spiritual matter; all things being done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: After which he ſhall ſing a Pſalm, and then one of the <hi>Stewards,</hi> or any other at their requeſt, ſhall begin Prayers, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the Confeſſion, the Lord's-Prayer, with the Collects that follow it, and a Thankſgiving after Prayers, and ſo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43505:28"/> conclude with a Pſalm, and a Collect; and then the <hi>Stewards,</hi> or one of them, ſhall call over the Names, and receive the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions; and about 8 of the Clock, all the Buſineſs being diſpatch'd, one of the <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> ſhall read over theſe <hi>Practical Rules,</hi> and the whole at leaſt Four times every Year.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Practical RULES <hi>to be obſerved by every.</hi> Member, <hi>and read at every</hi> Meeting, <hi>after Prayers, when the Names are called over.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. EVery <hi>Member</hi> of this <hi>Society</hi> ſhall heartily endeavour, through God's Grace, ſtrictly to obſerve the <hi>Lord</hi>'s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>Day,</hi> to ſanctifie it, and not to neglect, if in Health, the Publick Ordinances of the Church, and not to walk in Publick Walks or Places, where much People go, tho' he be in good Company, to avoid the giving of Scandal to good Chriſtians, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging the Wicked in their Ways.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To receive the Sacrament of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s-<hi>Supper</hi> frequently, and to attend the publick Service and Worſhip of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God on Week-days, as often as Conveniency will permit.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:43505:28"/>3. To watch ſtrictly, that by no means any Action of our Lives, nor yet any of our Words, may bring any Scandal on the Holy Religion we profeſs, being Juſt in all our Dealings. And each <hi>Member</hi> ſhall encourage, in their reſpective Families and Stations, all manner of Religious Family Duties.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That every one endeavour to keep his Soul in an habitual Frame of Prayer, by ſetting the Lord always before his Face, and by making Spiritual Reflections upon every Occurrence of Providence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we do not wound our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by a ſervile Compliance in wicked Company; but rather to reprove them, bearing Teſtimony to the Goſpel of Chriſt as far as Conſcience and Prudence do then permit us to do; and yet to ſhun all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Affectation and Moroſeneſs, and be of a civil and obliging Deportment to all Men.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To avoid all wicked Company when we have not a lawful Call; and to abſtain altogether from Play-Houſes and Gaming-Houſes, and from Ale-Houſes or Taverns, except when doing of Buſineſs does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and to arm our ſelves diligently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Exceſs upon any ſuch Occaſions.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:43505:29"/>7. To diſcountenance, as much as may be, any Diſcourſe being divulg'd, whereby any Prejudice may ariſe to any <hi>Member</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> or any other <hi>Society,</hi> or any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever. And to take ſpecial Care to avoid entring at any time into any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Diſputes, whether about Religion or Government, or other Matters, as being that which does <hi>inſenſibly betray to Paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. To pray for the <hi>Society</hi> in our private Prayers, that God would preſerve them, eſpecially from Hypocriſie and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Pride, which is the Worm at the Root that will blaſt all; and that we be helpful one to another.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To exerciſe Mortification and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial; and to keep a Monthly Faſt, if Conveniency will admit, or Neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; at leaſt to abſtain from ſome Meals ſometimes, which will much conduce to bring the Body into Subjection to the Soul.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That we endeavour that all our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe may be for <hi>the uſe of Edifying,</hi> and to <hi>miniſter Grace unto the Hearers,</hi> we will dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently apply our ſelves to the Reading the Holy Scriptures, and particularly ſuch parts as are moſt fitted to our Capacities and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; ſuch as, amongſt many others, is St. <hi>Matthew 5, 6, 7. Romans 12. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians 5, 6. 1 Theſſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:43505:29"/>11. That every one think it his indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible Duty to take care of one anothers Soul, and not to ſuffer Sin to lie upon our Brother; and therefore if any <hi>Member,</hi> by long abſenting himſelf from the Meeting, without known cauſe, does give juſt Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſuſpect him of too much indifference, that then no Perſon ſhall think himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd from the Obligation of ſtriving to reclaim him, unleſs there be ſome fit Perſon or Perſons, pitch'd upon by the <hi>Society,</hi> to go and do that Charitable Office, if there may be hope of his Recovery.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That we often conſider (with an awful Dread of God's Wrath) the ſad height to which the Sins of many are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in this our Nation, and the bleeding Diviſions thereof in Church and State, and that every Member be ready to do what upon conſulting with each other ſhall be thought adviſable towards the Puniſhment of <hi>publick Prophaneneſs,</hi> according as the good Laws of our Land require to be put in Execution, and in purſuant of the King's <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Proclamation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. To beware of raſhly-Judging or Cenſuring others who do not ſo much fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Holy Duties as our ſelves; or upon any other account to expreſs due Chriſtian
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43505:30"/> Charity to thoſe of good Converſation, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they diſſent from us. And to examine our ſelves every Night, that our Repentance may be ſincere, always evidenced by good Works.</p>
            <p n="14">14. If any <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Society</hi> be Sick, we do not forget to viſit him, and others, where we ſee it may be convenient, that we may comfort each other in this to a better Life.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That the Major-part of this <hi>Society</hi> may make what Alteration they ſhall think Neceſſary in theſe RULES; which done, they ſhall oblige each <hi>Member</hi> of this <hi>Society</hi> to performance, ſubſcribing his Name hereunto, thereby to declare his Approbation of, and his Reſolution and Endeavour to live up to them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>Shorter</hi> Practical RULES <hi>to be read at every</hi> Meeting <hi>when there is not time for the longer; and fit for every</hi> Member <hi>to get by heart.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. THat God's Glory be the end of all our Actions, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That we Worſhip Him in Spirit and in Truth, <hi>John</hi> 4. 24.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:43505:30"/>III. That we love God above all things, and our Neighbours as our ſelves, <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 30, 31.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That we endeavour to make the Word of God the Rule of all our Actions, <hi>Pſal. 191. 9. 105. John 5. 39. Rom.</hi> 15. 4.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That we keep the Lord's-Day Holy, <hi>Exod. 20. 8. Iſa.</hi> 58. 13.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That we ſtir up and exerciſe the Grace God hath given us, in going on from Virtue to Virtue, 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 5. 2 Pet. 1. 5, 6, 7, 8. 1 Theſſ.</hi> 3. 12.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That we Pray Frequently, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, Holy, and Perſevering, 1 <hi>Theſſ. 5. 17. Luke</hi> 18.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. To be Juſt in all our Dealings, <hi>Matt. 7. 12. Luke</hi> 6. 31.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. To receive the Holy Sacrament fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, 1 <hi>Cor. 11. 26. Luke</hi> 22. 19.</p>
            <p n="10">X. To have Poverty of Spirit, Meekneſs, and Humility, <hi>Matt. 5. 3, 5. Luke</hi> 14. 10.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. To watch againſt Cenſuring our Neighbours, <hi>Col. 3. 14. 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. To uſe our ſelves to holy Thoughts in all Places, <hi>Eph. 2. 5. Jer. 23. 23, 24. Heb. 4. 13. Pſal.</hi> 139. 23.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. To examine our ſelves every Night, <hi>Pſal. 4. 4. 2 Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. To be helpful one to another, <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 27.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:43505:31"/>XV. To Pray one for another, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 15, 16.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. To exerciſe Tenderneſs and Compaſſion to all Men, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 15.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. To ſhun all Occaſions of Evil, 1 <hi>Theſſ. 5. 22. 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. To ſubdue the Body by Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Matt. 6. 16. Luke 2. 32 Act.</hi> 13. 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. To make holy Reflections on our ſelves when we read the Bible, or hear the Word of God, <hi>James</hi> 1. 22, 23, 24.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. To endeavour to give no Scandal to the Holy Religion we profeſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 32.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. To avoid uncomely Jeſtings, and fooliſh Talking, <hi>Eph. 5. 4, 25. Col.</hi> 4. 5.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. To Judge none that do not ſo much frequent Holy Duties as our ſelves, <hi>Matt. 7. 1. Rom.</hi> 14. 13.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That we all endeavour to encourage pious Diſcourſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Meetings in our <hi>Societies,</hi> as well as enlarge it with ſuitable Members, <hi>Mal. 3. 16, 17. Col. 6. 9. Heb. 10. 25. James</hi> 5. 20.</p>
            <p>A Friendly Diſcourſe concerning Prophane Curſing and Swearing. Wherein is ſhewed the Heinouſneſs of thoſe Sins, and the Neceſſity of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons giving Information to the <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> Price Stitch'd, <hi>Two Pence.</hi> Sold at the ſame Place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43505:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
